A Guide to the Copies of Virginia Land Office records, 1743-1912
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Copies of Virginia Land Office records, 1743-1912
The Library of Virginia
LOI 12
.3 cu. ft (1 box)
Virginia. Land Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession LOI 12 transferred by the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1948.
Historical Information
The act which established the previous Land Office next hit passed the General Assembly on 22 June 1779. The register was the head of the Office and was appointed by joint ballot of both houses of the legislature.
Scope and Content
These records contain copies of court records, separated from the files with which they belong, sent in to support claims; copies of documents from the Land Office prepared either for internal use or on request and not retrieved; and copies of documents predating the establishment of the Land Office in 1779. Included in the last category are General Court records, 1747-1772; Council records, 1743-1774; and county court orders certiying importation claims, 1750-1779. Total years covered are 1743; 1745; 1747-1748; 1750; 1753-1756; 1758; 1760; 1763-1765; 1770; 1772-1775; 1779; 1783-1787; 1790; 1793; 1795-1796; 1805-1806; 1810; 1817-1818; 1821; 1823-1825; 1827; 1829-1830; 1840; 1847; 1849; 1853-1854; 1860; 1864-1865; 1870-1871; 1875; 1879-1883; 1887; 1913
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Copies of Virginia Land Office records, 1743-1914
Items are arranged by subject matter.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Land grants -- Virginia.; Rights of property -- Virginia.
Genre and Form Terms:
State government records.
Contents List
- Copies of Virginia Land Office Records, 1743-1914., Extent: 1 box.
  By subject
  - Copies, bounty certificates, 1875-1913. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Contains bounty certificates for land grants issued to John Conoll in 1783 and Captain Thomas Armistead in 1782. The first was copied in 1913 and the second in 1875.
    Arranged chronologically.
  - Copies, council documents, 1743-1774. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains a variety of council documents, including caveats issued against various individuals, orders of council, permission for a survey, and a memorial submitted by George Washington on behalf of a number of officers and soldiers for shares in 200,000 acres of land promised by Lt. Gov. Dinwiddie. Items are dated 1743, 1745, 1748, 1758, 1764, and 1772-1774.
  - Copies, court orders and decrees, 1776-1888. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains a variety of court orders and decrees related to land grants and warrants, including petitions for headright bounties, caveats issued against various individuals, documents regarding the guardianship of orphaned minors, and applications for the surveying or resurveying of land. Items are dated 1776, 1783, 1785, 1786, 1790, 1793, 1796, 1800, 1805, 1817, 1821, 1823-1825, 1829, 1853, 1854, 1860, 1865, 1870, 1871, 1875, 1879-1883, 1887, and 1888.
  - Copies, court orders pertaining to exportation rights, 1750-1779. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contains copies of court orders, including statements claiming land under the royal charter from Great Britain and deeds of assignment. Items are dated 1750, 1763, 1770, 1775, and 1779.
  - Copies, general court documents, 1747-1772. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Consists of petitions to the governor, lieutenant governor, and president of the council, for grants of land in various counties.
    Arranged in reverse chronological order.
    - David Dolton vs William Lucas, Albemarle Co, 1772.
    - John Colquist, Cumberland Co, 1764.
    - Charles Irby, Lunenburg Co, 1763.
    - Henry Sharpe, Sussex Co, 1760.
    - James Pittillo, Prince George Co, 1766.
    - Sylvanus Walker, Cumberland Co, 1754.
    - John Christian, Goochland Co, 1754.
    - James March, Nansemond Co, 1753.
    - Thomas Davenport, Goochland Co, 1749.
  - Copies, surveys, 1747-1772. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contains copies of a number of surveys prepared for individuals in several counties.
    - William Morrison, Albemarle Co, 1748.
    - Edward McGuire, Frederick Co, 1765.
    - James Buttaud, Monongalia Co, 1784.
    - Benjamin Johnson, Hanover Co, 1787.
    - Henry Banks, Randolph Co, 1787.
    - Richard Smyth, Randolph Co, 1794.
    - John Murphy, Lewis Co, 1818.
    - John Stricker, Ohio Co, 1787, 1829.
    - John Stricker, 1787.
    - Hezekiah Davidson, 1785.
    - Richard Smyth, Randolph Co, 1795.
    - John Smith, Montgomery Co, 1787.
    - Isaac Melcher, Monongalia Co, 1783.
    - Samuel Grove, Morgan Co, 1827.
    - Delilah A. E. Harvey, 1880.
    - James Williams, Monongalia Co, 1827.
    - Chapman and Burk, 1810.
    - John M. Falls, Augusta Co, 1756.
    - William Austin, Henry Co, 1784.
    - Christian Peters and others, Monroe Co, 1805,.
    - Moses Wilson, Lomax Co, 1784.
    - Harrison Hardman, Tyler Co, 1861,.
    - Joseph Peck, 1849.
  - Copies, warrants, 1840-1847. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Contains military warrants from 1840 for Aleck Saunders and William Shelby, and a warrant to survey the lands of Israil Smith from 1847.